<d:preface version="5.0" xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
           xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
           xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <?xml-stylesheet href="../css/style.css" type="text/css"?>
  <?dbhtml filename="preface/index.html" ?>
  <d:title>Preface</d:title>
  <d:para>
    This is a book on trigonometry, which, covers basics of trigonometry till high school
    level. It covers the most essential topics to take up a calculus course
    where knowledge of trigonometry is required. There is no specific purpose for
    writing this book. This is a book for self study and is not recommended for
    courses in schools and universities. I will try to cover as much as I can
    and will keep adding new material over a long period. I have no
    interest in writing a book in a fixed way which serves a university or
    college course as I have always love freedom.
  </d:para>
  <d:para>
    Trigonometry is probably one of the most fundamental subjects in Mathematics as
    further study of subjects like calculus and coordinate geometry.
    That is the primary reason I have chosen it to be the
    second subject in mathematics to be dealt with. It is very important to
    understand trigonometry for the readers if they want to advance further in
    mathematics. Trigonometry is a much easier subject compared to algebra.
    The reason is algebra comprises of different unrelated concepts like complex numbers, quadratic equations, matrices,
    determinants etc. while trigonometry is conerned about simple trigonometric functions triangle and circles. Trigonomtery is
    quite a coherent subject while algebra is chaotic.
  </d:para>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>Why I Wrote This Book?</d:title>
    <d:para>
      I wrote this book for myself! No, I did not write it for anybody else. My
      knowledge, which I have acquired by reading books written by many great
      mathematicians and authors and interactions with many intelligent people,
      is what has been put in the book. I have just tried to add my flavor to
      it. Think of it as notes for me. Just that I like to organize my notes so
      it has taken form of a book and nothing more. If you benefit from this
      then that is a pure coincidence and not intentional at all.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>How to Read This Book?</d:title>
    <d:para>
      No I will not simply tell that you must solve the problems. My advice would be
      more detailed. Every chapter will have theory. Read that first. Make sure
      you understand that. Of course, you have to meet the prerequisites for the
      book. Then, go on and try to solve the problems. In this book, there are
      no pure problems. Almost all have answers except those which are of
      similar kind and repetitive in nature for the sake of practice. If you
      can solve the problem then all good else look at the answer and try to
      understand that. Then, few days later take on the problem again. If you
      fail to understand the answer you can always email me with your work and
      I will try to answer to the best of my ability. However, if you have a
      local expert seek his/her advice first. Just that email is bad
      for mathematics. Someday I will develop an email system with support for
      scientific symbols and equations.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>Who Should Read This Book?</d:title>
    <d:para>
      Since this book is written for self study anyone with interest in trigonometry
      can read it. That does not mean that school or college students cannot
      read it. You need to be selective as to what you need for your particular
      requirements. This is mostly high school course with a little bit of
      lower classes' course thrown in with a bit of detail here and there.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>Prerequisite</d:title>
    <d:para>
      You should have knowledge till grade 10th course. Attempt has been made
      to keep it simple and give as much as background to the topic which is
      reasonable and required. However, not everything will be covered below
      grade 10.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>Goals for Readers</d:title>
    <d:para>
      The goal of for reading this book is becoming proficient in solving
      simple and basic problems of trigonometry. Another goal would be to be able to
      study other subjects which require this knowledge like algebra or
      calculus or coordinate geometry or other subjects. If you can solve 95%
      problems after 2 years of reading this book then you have achieved this
      goal.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      All of us possess a certain level of intelligence. At average any person
      can read this book. But what is most important is you have to have
      interest in the subject. Your interest gets multiplied with your
      intelligence and thus you will be more capable than you think you can
      be. One more point is focus and effort. It is not something new which I
      am telling but I am saying it again just to emphasize the point. Trust me
      if you are reading this book for just scoring a nice grade in your course
      then I have failed in my purpose of explaining my ideas. Grades should be byproduct of understanding not only memory. In
      general I do like open book exams for mathematics so that problem solving ability of student comes to forefront.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
  <d:simplesect>
    <d:title>Acknowledgments</d:title>
    <d:para>
      As with any book there are a lot of people involved with this book but
      not in traditional sense of a typical book. I have written this book
      using Docbook thus Norman Walsh deserves
      praise. <d:code>xsltproc</d:code> has been used to process
      <d:code>xml</d:code> to <d:code>html</d:code> and it is a wonderful piece
      of software written by James Clark. While I used sphinx for algebra I am using docbook and MathML for trigonometry. Only
      Firefox supports MathML but it allows very fast rendering of Math so please use Firefox. I have also enabled MathJax so
      rendering will be a bit slower on other browsers. Please SWITCH to Firefox as it protects your privacy as well and supports
      open internet.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      There are a lot of diagrams in this text and those have been drawn using
      Tikz. Thanks for its developers Till Tantau and Christian Feuersaenger
      along with all the contributors for creating such a wonderful piece of
      vector graphics library for TeX. I also use Asymptote a lot for drawing
      pictures, which, has been developed by Andy Hammerlindl, John C. Bowman
      and Tom Prince. Many thanks to these gentleman.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      I must say thanks to my family particularly to my parents, wife and my
      son whose precious time I have taken to write this book and gave them
      numerous trouble in general. They have been the major force which
      supported while writing it. This book would not have been possible
      without their support.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      There have been many teachers in my life who have helped me with various
      lessons in life and otherwise. I will try to remember all of them here
      and seek forgiveness if I miss anyone. My math teachers Yogendra Yadav,
      Hriday Nayaran Singh and Satyanand Satyarthi have helped me a lot with
      basics of Mathematics. Anurag Johri, Sirnivasa Kotu, Shreyas Majthia and
      Mufti Mohammed for their technical discussions and insight into
      programming. My professors S. Sen, S. Sengupta and T. K. Basu for showing
      faith in me during troubled times.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      I am not native English speaker and it has gone through only one pair of
      eyes thus you should expect all kinds of errors, particularly related to
      punctuation. I would be glad if you could report all errors, suggestions
      and feedback to me at<d:email>shivshankar.dayal@gmail.com</d:email> and
      those will be incorporated. <d:ulink
      url="https://www.languagetool.org/"><d:citetitle>Language
      Tool</d:citetitle></d:ulink> has been used for grammar checks and all as
      my English is pathetic, so you know whom to blame or appraise for mistakes.
    </d:para>
    <d:para>
      Although I would like to give a pdf version of the book for download but
      the content keep changing and there will be just too many versions of the
      book. Thus, please read html version until a final release can be done.
    </d:para>
  </d:simplesect>
</d:preface>
